MAHESH MUPPASANI

Full Stack Engineer

mahesh.muppasani007@gmail.com https://linkedin.com/in/mahesh-muppasani/ https://maheshmuppasani.vercel.app/ +1989491-1302 Ypsilanti. MI. 48197. USA

Full Stack Engineer with 5+ years of experience in automating businesses, optimizing application performance, and web development. Recognized for exceptional contributions to customer satisfaction and efficient management of critical functions. Proficient in Node.js, Express.js, React.js, Angular, MySQL, MSSQL, MongoDB etc.

Work Experience

Full Stack Engineer (Internship)

BigLynx Inc | Bellevue, WA, US

Jan 2024 - Nov 2024

- Automated the generation and distribution of weekly business reports by integrating Dynamics 365 CRM with a custom Node.js application, reducing manual effort by 40%.
- Optimized application performance by identifying bottlenecks and implementing caching strategies in the back-end, resulting in an improved response times of 25%.

IT Support Engineer (Part-time)

Jan 2023 - Dec 2023

Central Michigan University | Mt.Pleasant, MI, US

- Developed and supported the university's website by improving page load times by 25% faster, enhancing accessibility and scalability to handle over 10,000 concurrent users.
- Integrated Tableau to develop interactive dashboards for the administrator portal, enabling real-time visualization of key metrics such as student enrollments and semester trends which improved data accessibility and reduced reporting time by 30%, empowering administrators to make faster, data-driven decisions.

Web Developer (Full-time)

Aug 2021 - Dec 2022

Innova Solutions | Hyderabad, India

- Reduced a remarkable 100% manual work for processing supplementary product orders by developing an application for administrators.
- The system seamlessly automates order fulfillment, reducing average processing time by 80%, optimizes inventory control, decreasing stock discrepancies by 35%, among other critical functions.

Associate Web Developer (Full-time)

Dec 2019 - Aug 2021

Innova Solutions | Hyderabad, India

- Automated the order process for a leading pharmaceutical company by developing "Nutrascriptives Direct", a cutting-edge
 e-commerce application, increasing sales by 50%. The platform streamlined product ordering, improving user experience
 and boosting customer satisfaction by 70%.
- Terraformed an inventory tracking application for stakeholders from ASP.NET server pages to modern React with TypeScript and Node.js with zero downtime, improving performance by 75% and reducing page load times by 60%.

Projects

BigLynx CRM Portal

Jan 2024 - Nov 2024

- Developed a customizable CRM portal using Node.js, PostgreSQL and Dynamics 365, enabling streamlined customer data management and workflow automation, improving system's efficiency by 30%.
- Designed and integrated Power BI dashboards to provide real-time insights on sales performance and customer trends, accelerating decisions by 20%.
- Optimized backend performance by identifying bottlenecks and implementing caching strategies using redis, resulting in a 25% improvement in response times and system reliability.

CMU Website Jan 2023 - Dec 2023

• Developed and supported a responsive website using Figma, Node.js, MySQL, and React.js for Central Michigan University, reducing page load times by 25% and improving user satisfaction for more than 10,000 users.

• Integrated Tableau dashboards to visualize key metrics, including student enrollments, course progress, and semester trends, enabling 30% faster decision making for administrators.

MH Fulfilment Aug 2021 - Dec 2022

- Developed "MH Fulfillment", an administrator application for a leading pharmaceutical company using Node.js and React.js, enabling efficient processing of 8,000+ customer orders per month.
- This application witnessed an incredible growth in average order volumes by 39%.

Nutrascriptives Direct

Dec 2019 - Aug 2021

- Developed "Nutrascriptives Direct", a robust e-commerce application using Node.js, ReactJS, Semantic UI, and GraphQL APIs, automating the supplement ordering process for patients, reducing the manual labor work by 60% and achieving 100% order accuracy.
- It established a significant increase in sales revenue for the client with an exceptional growth rate of 41%.

University Management System (Freelance Project))

Oct 2024 - Dec 2024

- Developed a comprehensive University Management System using Node.js, React.js, and MySQL, enabling the system to manage student records, course enrollments, and faculty schedules in a single portal with multi-user roles.
- The system improved operational efficiency by 90%, reduced manual data handling time by 100%, and improved accessibility for tons of users compared to the manual system.

Volunteer Experience

SCRUM Master Oct 2021 - Dec 2022

Innova Solutions

As the Scrum Master for the Fulfilment application development, I orchestrated a high-performing team, driving project
completion 2 months ahead of the projected deadline. Through deliberate leadership and fostering collaboration, our team
generated a remarkable 20% improvement in project efficiency and delivered 15% cost savings while ensuring the
project's remarkable success.

Front End Panel Recruiter

Aug 2021 - Dec 2022

Innova Solutions

Innova Solutions

• Played a pivotal role in the recruitment process at Innova Solutions by taking over 100+ technical interviews as a front-end panel member, helping the firm to filter and onboard the applicants reflects in 30% hiring efficiency.

Technical Mentor – Web Development Training Program

Aug 2021 - Feb 2022

Under my mentorship at Innova Solutions, I guided a team of 5 trainee engineers, facilitating their mastery of essential
web technologies, including JavaScript, ReactJS, and NodeJS. The team was able to deliver three client projects ahead of
schedule, and customers were able to achieve a 29% increase in revenue.

Core Skills

C, C++, JavaScript (ES6+), TypeScript, HTML, CSS, React.js, Redux.js, Vue.js, Angular, NgRx, RxJS, Tailwind CSS, Bootstrap, Material-UI, Styled Components, Semantic UI, Webpack, Vite, Babel, ESLint, Prettier, Gulp.js, REST API, GraphQL, Apollo Client, Apollo Server, Axios, Fetch API, Socket.IO, Express.js, Node.js, Python, MySQL, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Dynamics 365 CRM, MSSQL, MariaDB, Sequelize, Mongoose, JWT, OAuth2, Bcrypt, Auth0, Firebase Authentication, Swagger, Jest, Nodemon, Multer, Postman, Git, GitLab, Lighthouse, Responsive Design, Developer Tools, WebSockets, SignalR, Agile, SCRUM, Waterfall

Education

Central Michigan University

Jan 2023 - Dec 2024

Master of Science in Information Systems

K L University

Jul 2016 - May 2020

Bachelor of Electronics and Communication Engineering

Awards

Best Intern of the Year Aug 2024

BigLynx Inc

Awarded "Best Intern of the Year" at BigLynx Inc. for exceptional contributions to the development of the BigLynx CRM Portal, improving client efficiency by 30% and enhancing system performance and decision-making capabilities.

Student Contribution Award

Sep 2023

Central Michigan University

Developed and demonstrated Tableau dashboards for administrators at the CMU Innovation Summit, where I was recognized with the outstanding "Student Contribution Award" for enhancing data accessibility and driving actionable insights for university operations.

Customer Champion Award

Oct 2021

Innova Solutions

Received the Customer Champion Award in recognition of exceptional contributions by guiding the team in completing 8 weeks of tickets in just 4 weeks and fostering customer satisfaction.